A Guide to the Byron Nelson Cooper Papers, 1925-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Byron Nelson Cooper Papers, 1925-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1973-004
9.0 cu. ft. 6 boxes
Correspondence; writings; research records; administrative, instructional, and consulting files; and photographs of Byron Nelson Cooper, professor of geology and head of Virginia Polytechnic Institute's Department of Geological Sciences from 1946 to 1971.
Cooper, Byron Nelson, 1912-1971
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Byron Nelson Cooper Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1973, 1977, and 1980.
Biographical Note
Byron Nelson Cooper was born the son of Frank L. and Stella P. Lynch Cooper in Plainfield, Indiana, on August 19, 1912. After graduating from DePauw University in 1934, Cooper earned his master's and doctoral degrees at the University of Iowa. Both his master's thesis (1935) and doctoral dissertation (1937) focused on topics relating to the geology of southwestern Virginia. While gathering research data in Southwest Virginia, Cooper met and married Elizabeth Doyne, of Pulaski County. (The couple would have two children.) Upon completion of his Ph.D., Cooper served as assistant professor of geology at Wichita University from 1937 to 1942, then as associate geologist of the Virginia Geological Survey for four years, before being named head of the Department of Geological Sciences at Virginia Polytechnic Institute in 1946.
Cooper became an active advocate for his department, building a nationally recognized program from what had been a fledgling operation. He also promoted the study of geology--particularly Appalachian geology--among the larger lay and professional community through speaking engagements and field trips. Cooper's consulting services were frequently sought by business and industrial concerns throughout Virginia, and he often assisted local governments, particularly with issues relating to water supply. He served on the Advisory Council on Virginia's Economy and the Governor's Advisory Council on Geology and was an active member of several professional organizations.
Byron Nelson Cooper died in his campus office on March 26, 1971.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of Byron Nelson Cooper, head of Virginia Polytechnic Institute's Department of Geological Sciences from 1946 to 1971. Included are correspondence, writings, research data, and photographs, largely relating to Appalachian geology, particularly that of southwestern Virginia.
Arrangement
The collection largely retains Cooper's original order, though a few changes have been made for clarity, and an assortment of unfiled materials have either been incorporated into existing files or added as new files. Among these previously unsorted materials are most of the collection's photographs and negatives. The collection is divided into two series:
Series I. Subject Files, 1925-1971. Cooper's subject files contain materials relating to the consulting work he performed for various businesses, industries, and local governments; his activities with various professional organizations; and both his instructional and administrative duties as head of Virginia Tech's Department of Geological Sciences. Included are correspondence and memoranda, drafts of research papers, research data and notes; preparatory materials for tours, talks, and publications; maps; printed materials; and photographs. Also included is a single folder relating to Cooper's personal life. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject. In cases in which a folder contains only a titled article or speech text, the file title has been placed in quotation marks.
Series II. Photographs and Negatives, 1953-ca. 1970. The items within this series were among materials in Cooper's papers that had remained largely unsorted and unfiled. The series consists largely of images of geological samples and sites, though it also includes photos of students, facilities, and general scenery. Also included are two short, unidentified 16mm films. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject, with a folder of miscellaneous images near the end.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following item was removed from Cooper's papers and added to the Historical Map Collection:
Blacksburg, Va. Zoning Map. [Blacksburg, VA?: s.n.], 1968.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; Geology; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Science and Technology; University Archives; University History; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Series I. Subject Files, 1925-1971
  - Ackermann, E. H., 1962 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Advisory Committee on Geology, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Advisory Committee on the Virginia Economy, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Airport - Buchanan County, Virginia, 1965 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Allis-Chalmers Manufacturing Company, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - meeting, 1956 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - American Association of Petroleum Geologists guidebook, 1959-1965 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - American Geological Institute, 1949-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
  - American Zinc Exploration Company, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Analysis of bedrock geology - Pulaski County, Virginia, 1969 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - "Anhydrite in the Plasterco-Saltville-Chatham Hill Area, Smyth and Washington Counties, Virginia," 1968 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - "Appalachian Folding: a Control of Paleozoic Sedimentation in the Appalachian Geosyncline," 1952 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Appalachian geology, 1960-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Appalachian Geology (Geology 503), 1970, n.d. (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Appalachian region - floods, ca. 1968 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Appalachian shales, 1969 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - "The Appalachian Structural and Topographic Front Between Narrows and Beckley, Virginia and West Virginia," n.d. (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Argabrite v. Thompson, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Atlantic-Richfield Company digitizing equipment, 1968 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Austinville - Ivanhoe ore bodies, 1963 (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Austinville, Virginia - rainfall records, 1958-1962 (Box-folder 1-21)
  - Baillio, Robert H., 1962 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Bane Dome, Virginia, 1947 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Barium Reduction Corporation, 1952-1953, n.d. (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Bates, Robert L., 1960-1961 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Beatrice Mine maps, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Beaver Products Company mine layout (North Holston, Virginia), 1930 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Beck Tunnel to Iron Blossom, n.d. (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Bethlehem Mines, 1962 (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Bevan, Arthur, 1954-1958, n.d. (Box-folder 1-30)
  - The Big Survey, 1968-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 1-31)
  - "The Big Survey: Nelson County, Virginia," 1970 (Box-folder 1-32)
  - Big Walker Mountain Tunnel, 1968-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 1-33)
  - Blacksburg Citizens for Better Government, n.d. (Box-folder 1-34)
  - Blacksburg-Pulaski synclinorium, n.d. (Box-folder 1-35)
  - Blacksburg, Virginia - roads and planning, 1963-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 1-36)
  - Blaw-Knox Construction Company - core drill locations, 1952 (Box-folder 1-37)
  - Bonner Springs, 1960 (Box-folder 1-38)
  - Broadway, Virginia - sewage lagoons, 1961-1962, n.d. (Box-folder 1-39)
  - Brown, William R., 1946-1948 (Box-folder 1-40)
  - "Brushite and Taranakite from Pig Holes Cave, Giles County, Virginia" by John W. Murray and Richard V. Dietrich, 1956 (Box-folder 1-41)
  - Bulletin 62: captions for illustrations, n.d. (Box-folder 1-42)
  - Calco No. 1 Kipps Well daily formation reports, 1949 (Box-folder 1-43)
  - Calver, James L. (state geologist), 1959 (Box-folder 1-44)
  - Canadian Shield - map, n.d. (Box-folder 1-45)
  - "Careers in the Mineral Industries" by Thomas T. Read, 1941 (Box-folder 1-46)
  - Celanese Fibers Company drawings, 1968 (Box-folder 1-47)
  - Cement resources, 1963, n.d. (Box-folder 1-48)
  - "The Cenotaph of the V.P.I. Memorial," n.d. (Box-folder 1-49)
  - Chevron research lab, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 1-50)
  - Clintwood, Virginia - groundwater resources, 1948 (Box-folder 1-51)
  - Coal - Southwest Virginia, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 1-52)
  - Colonna and Company, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1-53)
  - Consulting work, 1948-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 1-54)
  - Cooper, Byron Nelson - personal, 1937-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 1-55)
  - "Critical Review of Literature on the Toxicity of Industrial Wastes and Their Components to Fish," 1953 (Box-folder 1-56)
  - Decker, Charles E., 1945-1947, n.d. (Box-folder 1-57)
  - "Décollement Folding and Thrusting in the Appalachians," n.d. (Box-folder 1-58)
  - Derring Hall Addition Subcommittee, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 1-59)
  - Derring Hall dedication, 1969, n.d. (Box-folder 1-60)
  - Diamond Plastics Industries, 1963 (Box-folder 1-61)
  - Discharge logs for unidentified stations, 1966-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 1-62)
  - "Discovery of Folsom-Like Arrowpoint and Artifacts of Mastodon Bone in Southwest Virginia" by R. W. Pickle, 1946 (Box-folder 1-63)
  - Dolostone, n.d. (Box-folder 1-64)
  - Eagle-Pilcher Company, 1956 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Eagle Rock Lime Company, 1947-1954, n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
  - "Effect of Stratigraphic Variations on Mining of High-Calcium Limestone at Kimballton, Virginia," 1949 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Electron Microprobe Committee, 1965 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Engineers' Club of the Virginia Peninsula, 1954, n.d. (Box-folder 2-5)
  - "Erosion of Public Trust," 1971, n.d. (Box-folder 2-6)
  - "Evaluation of Stone Reserves of Virginian Limestone - Limestone Corporation, Klotz, Virginia," 1962 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Field books, [1962-1965] (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Field books, [1967-1971] (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Fishburn Land Committee, 1954, n.d. (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Foote Mineral Company - Horton Summit property, 1951-1955, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Fortran cards (map area calculations), n.d. (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Freeport Sulphur Company, 1964, n.d. (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Friendsville area, 1951, n.d. (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Fishersville, Virginia anomaly, n.d. (Box-folder 2-15)
  - "Gastropoda of the Middle Ordovician Peery and Murfreesboro Formations of Virginia and Tennessee," n.d. (Box-folder 2-16)
  - General Stone and Materials Corporation, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Geneva Works, 1953-1955, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-18)
  - "Geologic Control of Rainfall - Runoff Relations in the Peak Creek Watershed, Pulaski and Wythe Counties, Virginia," 1969 (Box-folder 2-19)
  - "Geologic Enterprise in Virginia - Present and Future," n.d. (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Geologic sections - measurements, n.d. (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Geologic sections - Virginia and Tennessee, 1948-1970, [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Geological inquiries (general), 1948-1970 (Box-folder 2-23)
  - Geological profiles, n.d. (Box-folder 2-24)
  - Geological Society of America - Southeastern Section field trips, 1957 (Box-folder 2-25)
  - Geological Society of America - Southeastern Section meeting, 1962-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 2-26)
  - Geological Society of America - Southeastern Section meeting proposal, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2-27)
  - "Geology and Industrial Development," n.d. (Box-folder 2-28)
  - "Geology and Industrial Development in Virginia," 1954, n.d. (Box-folder 2-29)
  - "Geology and Pollution," n.d. (Box-folder 2-30)
  - Geology bibliography, 1956-1966, [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-31)
  - Geology course materials, 1954-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 2-32)
  - Geology field camp - Saltville, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Geology field tours (non-VPI), 1950-1971 (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Geology - miscellaneous correspondence, 1948-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Geology - miscellaneous notes, n.d. (Box-folder 3-4)
  - "Geology of the Johns Creek Reservoir and Damsite, Craig County, Virginia," ca. 1948 (Box-folder 3-5)
  - "Geology of the Salt and Gypsum Deposits in the Saltville Area, Smyth and Washington Counties, Virginia," n.d. (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Geology professional organizations and conferences, 1948-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Geology students and alumni, 1953-1971 (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Giles County, Virginia, n.d. (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Grand Appalachian Excursion, 1961, n.d. (Box-folder 3-10)
  - "Ground Water: Its Occurrence and Utility," 1966 (Box-folder 3-11)
  - Guidebook proofs, 1961 (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Gulf Oil Corporation, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 3-13)
  - Harrisonburg, Virginia - water supply, 1934-1958, n.d. (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Highway engineering, 1951 (Box-folder 3-15)
  - Holston River - North Fork, 1954-1956, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 3-16)
  - Holston River - North Fork: report by the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia,1955, n.d. (Box-folder 3-17)
  - Holston River - North Fork: sanitary waste analysis, 1937-1951 (Box-folder 3-18)
  - Holston River - North Fork: Virginia State Water Control Board, 1953-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 3-19)
  - Horton's Summit, Virginia - maps, 1952, n.d. (Box-folder 3-20)
  - "How to Catch a Genius," n.d. (Box-folder 3-21)
  - Howell, B. F., 1945-1946 (Box-folder 3-22)
  - Huntley and Huntley, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 3-23)
  - Hutcheson, John Redd memorial, 1962 (Box-folder 3-24)
  - "Industrial Quartzite in Virginia," 1951 (Box-folder 3-25)
  - International Mineralogical Association, 1962 (Box-folder 3-26)
  - Iron ore - newspaper clippings, 1960 (Box-folder 3-27)
  - Iron ore - speeches, n.d. (Box-folder 3-28)
  - Iron ore studies, 1960-1961, n.d. (Box-folder 3-29)
  - Island Creek Coal Company - drill reports, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 3-30)
  - Ivanhoe, Virginia - surface subsidence map, 1958 (Box-folder 3-31)
  - James River Basin, 1947, n.d. (Box-folder 3-32)
  - James River Hydrate and Supply Company, 1962-1967 (Box-folder 3-33)
  - Lerch Brothers and Wakefield tests, 1963-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 3-34)
  - Lesure, Frank, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 3-35)
  - Lightweight aggregate, 1964-1966, n.d. (Box-folder 3-36)
  - Limestone, 1955-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 3-37)
  - "Location Report for Interstate Highway 77 - Princeton, W. Va. to Elkin, N.C." by J. E. Grainer Company, 1966 (Box-folder 3-38)
  - Locher Silica Corporation, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 3-39)
  - Lone Star Cement Corporation, 1958-1965 (Box-folder 3-40)
  - Luray Textile, 1964-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 3-41)
  - Manganese, 1948-1954 (Box-folder 3-42)
  - "Manganiferous Quartzite Deposits in the Lick Mountains - Wythe County, Virginia," 1966 (Box-folder 3-43)
  - Maps, Topographic (USGS) - Tennessee, 1925-1942, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 3-44)
  - Maps, Topographic (USGS) - other states, 1932-1954, n.d. (Box-folder 3-45)
  - Maps, Unidentified, n.d. (Box-folder 3-46)
  - Maps - Virginia (partial), 1930-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 3-47)
  - Marble companies, 1959-1962, n.d. (Box-folder 3-48)
  - Marble Valley Pumped Storage Project, 1969 (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Martin Processing Company, 1963, n.d. (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Martinsburg, West Virginia, 1964 (Box-folder 4-3)
  - "Martinsburg and 'Athens' Shale Formations Along Interstate Route 81 from Mason Creek to Hollins in Roanoke County, Virginia," 1962 (Box-folder 4-4)
  - Mathieson Chemical Corporation, 1953-1969, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 4-5)
  - Mathieson Chemical Corporation - core drilling log reports, 1960, n.d. (Box-folder 4-6)
  - Mathieson Chemical Corporation: record of hearing, 1956 (Box-folder 4-7)
  - Mathieson Chemical Corporation - T. T. Taylor property, 1963 (Box-folder 4-8)
  - "The Max Meadows Breccias: A Reply," n.d. (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Max Meadows Oil Company, 1968, n.d. (Box-folder 4-10)
  - McGill, William H. (state geologist), 1949-1954 (Box-folder 4-11)
  - Meadow Creek Corporation, 1948-1949, n.d. (Box-folder 4-12)
  - "Memorandum on Limestone Resources in the Swords Creek Area, Virginia," 1951 (Box-folder 4-13)
  - "Memorandum Report on Possibilities for Oil in the Vicinity of Speedwell, Tenn.," 1947 (Box-folder 4-14)
  - Middlesboro, Kentucky, 1968 (Box-folder 4-15)
  - Mineral depletion allowances, 1965, n.d. (Box-folder 4-16)
  - Mineral Industries Journal, 1957-1959, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 4-17)
  - Mineral industries personnel in Virginia, 1951, n.d. (Box-folder 4-18)
  - Mineral Research Laboratory, 1964-1965, n.d. (Box-folder 4-19)
  - Minerals Development Corporation, 1963 (Box-folder 4-20)
  - Mississippian correlations, 1945, n.d. (Box-folder 4-21)
  - Montgomery County, Virginia - elevations, n.d. (Box-folder 4-22)
  - "Mountain City - Doe Mountain Properties," 1969 (Box-folder 4-23)
  - Murrill, Ashley, 1952 (Box-folder 4-24)
  - National Crushed Stone Association, 1962 (Box-folder 4-25)
  - National Science Foundation, 1965-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 4-26)
  - National Science Foundation - equipment, 1962, n.d. (Box-folder 4-27)
  - National Science Foundation - undergraduate research participation in the geological sciences, 1958 (Box-folder 4-28)
  - Nelson, Bruce, 1956-1963 (Box-folder 4-29)
  - "New Virginia Mineral Resources Map Published," n.d. (Box-folder 4-30)
  - Newman, Walter S., 1948-1959 (Box-folder 4-31)
  - Newman, Walter S. - Inaugural Committee, 1948-1949, n.d. (Box-folder 4-32)
    [includes typed letters signed by Dwight D. Eisenhower, Milton S. Eisenhower, James W. Fulbright, George C. Marshall, and Harry F. Byrd]
  - Norfolk and Western Railway Company, 1953-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 4-33)
  - Norris, E. B., 1947-1948 (Box-folder 4-34)
  - Norris silt range movements - map, n.d. (Box-folder 4-35)
  - Ordovician Subcommittee on Stratigraphical Paleontology, National Research Council, 1947-1949, n.d. (Box-folder 4-36)
  - Pardue, Louis A., 1959 (Box-folder 4-37)
  - "Patterns for Mineral Research," 1964 (Box-folder 4-38)
  - Pegmatites in the Bedford Area, Virginia," n.d. (Box-folder 4-39)
  - "Penecontemporaneous Down-Dip Slump Structures in Middle Ordovician Limestone, Harrisonburg, Virginia," n.d. (Box-folder 4-40)
  - Penrose Medal Committee, Geological Society of America, 1957, n.d. (Box-folder 4-41)
  - "Petrology, Petrography, and Origin of the Shady Dolomite in the Cripple Creek Area, Wythe County, Virginia" by David Allen Aronson, ca. 1968, [2 folders] (Box-folder 4-42)
  - Pollution, 1969, n.d. (Box-folder 4-43)
  - "Preparation of Iron Ore Concentrates of Commercial Grade from Iron-Bearing Sandstones in Western Virginia," n.d. (Box-folder 4-44)
  - "The Price Mountain Well - Montgomery County, Virginia," 1949 (Box-folder 4-45)
  - "Primary Dolomite?" 1955 (Box-folder 4-46)
  - "Profile of the Folded Appalachians of Western Virginia," 1968 (Box-folder 4-47)
  - "Profile of the Folded Appalachians of Western Virginia," n.d. (Box-folder 4-48)
  - "Prospecting for Oil Near Blacksburg, Virginia," n.d. (Box-folder 4-49)
  - Pulaski County, 1967-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 4-50)
  - Pulaski faults, 1969-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 4-51)
  - "The Quandary in University Management of Environmental Sciences," n.d. (Box-folder 5-1)
  - Radford Arsenal - well,1962, n.d. (Box-folder 5-2)
  - Radford stone sand report, 1958 (Box-folder 5-3)
  - "The Raines Hollow Reservoir Project," 1957 (Box-folder 5-4)
  - "Regional Geophysical Data and their Relation to the Appalachians in Central and Western Virginia" by Robert W. Johnson Jr., 1957 (Box-folder 5-5)
  - "Relation of Stratigraphy to Structure in the Southern Appalachians," 1964 (Box-folder 5-6)
  - "Relation of the Pulaski and Seven Springs Faults in Southwestern Virginia," n.d. (Box-folder 5-7)
  - "Report of Investigation of Geological Conditions in the Vicinity of the Williamsburg Reservoir," 1963 (Box-folder 5-8)
  - "Report of Investigation of Proposed Dam Site for Waste Sludge Impoundment at Covington, Virginia," 1963 (Box-folder 5-9)
  - "Report on Foundation Conditions at Southwest Wing of Appomattox River Dam," 1967 (Box-folder 5-10)
  - "Report on Grecian Marble Slabs Used in the New Rockland County Courthouse, New York," 1963 (Box-folder 5-11)
  - "Report on Petrographic Examination of No. 1 Arctic Quartz Sample Submitted 7/28," 1967 (Box-folder 5-12)
  - "Research and Effective Teaching in the Geological Sciences," 1958 (Box-folder 5-13)
  - "Review of the Geologic-Hydrologic Conditions in the Marble Valley Area, Virginia," 1969 (Box-folder 5-14)
  - Richmond Southern Alabama Dam aggregate, n.d. (Box-folder 5-15)
  - Roanoke County blasting project damage claims, 1962 (Box-folder 5-16)
  - Roanoke Electric Steel, 1959 (Box-folder 5-17)
  - Roanoke, Virginia, 1960-1965, n.d. (Box-folder 5-18)
  - Roanoke - wells, 1966 (Box-folder 5-19)
  - Rock mechanics, n.d. (Box-folder 5-20)
  - Rock samples from Penn Laird, Virginia area, n.d. (Box-folder 5-21)
  - Rockydale quarries, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 5-22)
  - "Role of Subsidence in the Evolution of Folded Mountains," 1958 (Box-folder 5-23)
  - "The Role of the Division of Industrial Development and the Advisory Council on the Virginia Economy on Research for Industrial Development," 1959 (Box-folder 5-24)
  - "Roles of Fossils in Appalachian Stratigraphy," 1971 (Box-folder 5-25)
  - "Rose Hill Oil Field, Virginia," 1948 (Box-folder 5-26)
  - Saltville brine field, 1960, n.d. (Box-folder 5-27)
  - Saltville - chemical effluents and North Fork of Holston River, 1953, n.d. (Box-folder 5-28)
  - Saltville - muck dam, river bridge, and highway photographs, 1953 (Box-folder 5-29)
  - Saltville - muck pond discharge, 1954, n.d. (Box-folder 5-30)
  - Saltville - salt reserves, 1951-1958, n.d. (Box-folder 5-31)
  - Salvation Army - Sinking Creek Valley well, 1962 (Box-folder 5-32)
  - Science in Virginia high schools questionnaire, n.d. (Box-folder 5-33)
  - Seale, Fred - Powell Valley, Tennessee, 1948-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 5-34)
  - Sedimentation doctoral program proposal, 1960-1961, n.d. (Box-folder 5-35)
  - "Shales in Appalachian Geology," n.d. (Box-folder 5-36)
  - "Significance of Hayter Fans in the Geomorphic History of Western Virginia," 1950 (Box-folder 5-37)
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1945-1950 (Box-folder 5-38)
  - Smyth County Community Hospital site, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 5-39)
  - Southwestern State Hospital (Marion, Virginia) water supply, 1958-1959, n.d. (Box-folder 5-40)
  - Southwestern United States - descriptions of illustration plates, n.d. (Box-folder 5-41)
  - Stanolind Oil and Gas Company, 1947 (Box-folder 5-42)
  - "Status of Mississippian Stratigraphy in the Central and Northern Appalachian Region," 1948 (Box-folder 5-43)
  - Steel in western Virginia, 1957-1961, n.d. (Box-folder 5-44)
  - Steel mill in Radford, Virginia - feasibility, 1956-1958, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 5-45)
  - Steel mill - market survey, ca. 1956 (Box-folder 5-46)
  - Steel mill potential in western Virginia, 1957-1958, n.d. (Box-folder 5-47)
  - Stone Products Corporation, 1963 (Box-folder 5-48)
  - "Stratigraphy of the Pearsiburg Syncline Area, Giles County, Virginia" by H. M. Whitman, 1960 (Box-folder 5-49)
  - Structural and Tectonic Principles book review, 1966 (Box-folder 5-50)
  - Studies of Appalachian geology: central and southern, 1967, n.d. (Box-folder 5-51)
  - "Suggestions regarding an oil and gas act for Virginia," 1949 (Box-folder 5-52)
  - "Summary of Activities of the Geological Survey," [1955] (Box-folder 5-53)
  - Tectonics, 1968 (Box-folder 5-54)
  - Thomasville Stone and Limestone Company, 1953-1966 (Box-folder 5-55)
  - Timberville, Virginia - cave-ins, 1961-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 5-56)
  - Toms Creek core drilling project, 1952, n.d. (Box-folder 5-57)
  - "Trilobites from the Lower Champlainian Formations of the Appalachian Valley," n.d. (Box-folder 5-58)
  - Underground disposal of effluent, 1953-1957 (Box-folder 6-1)
  - Union Bag-Camp Paper Corporation - Dismal Swamp property, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 6-2)
  - United Plastic Corporation, 1962 (Box-folder 6-3)
  - United States v. Cannelton Sewer Pipe Company, 1960 (Box-folder 6-4)